<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE pkgmetadata SYSTEM "http://www.gentoo.org/dtd/metadata.dtd">
<pkgmetadata>
<herd>kde</herd>
<use>
	<flag name="amazon">Enable support for downloading covers from amazon.com</flag>
	<flag name="cdaudio">Enable cdaudio functionality</flag>
	<flag name="daap">
		Enable the scripts for music sharing through DAAP. This flag adds
		dependencies on <pkg>www-servers/mongrel</pkg> to allow sharing of
		the Amarok music collection through DAAP protocol. Please note
		that turning this flag off has no effect on DAAP browsing.
	</flag>
	<flag name="ifp">Enable support for iRiver devices access through libifp</flag>
	<flag name="mp3tunes">Enable mp3tunes integration</flag>
	<flag name="mp4">
		Build the TagLib plugin for writing tags in Mp4 container files
		(m4a). Please note that by enabling this USE flag, the resulting
		package will not be redistributable, as it links to
		<pkg>media-libs/libmp4v2</pkg>, distributed under a
		GPL-incompatible license.
	</flag>
	<flag name="mtp">Enable support for libMTP (Plays4Sure) devices access through libmtp</flag>
	<flag name="njb">Enable support for NJB (Creative) devices access through libnjb</flag>
	<flag name="python">
		Install the Amarok scripts written in Python, depending on
		<pkg>dev-python/PyQt</pkg>. At the moment the only script
		installed by this flag is the webcontrol script.
	</flag>
	<flag name="real">
		Build the Helix engine for Amarok, linked against
		<pkg>media-video/realplayer</pkg>. This is an alternative engine
		to the xine one, which supports a different set of formats. Only
		available for x86 architecture as it uses the binary version of
		RealPlayer. Please note that by enabling this USE flag, the resulting
		package will not be redistributable, as it links to the non-GPL compatible
		RealPlayer.
	</flag>
	<flag name="semantic-desktop">
		Semantic desktop allows for storage of digital informationand its
		metadata to allow the user to express his personal mental models, making
		all information become intuitively accessible
	</flag>
	<flag name="visualization">
		Support visualization plugins through <pkg>media-libs/libvisual</pkg>
	</flag>
</use>
</pkgmetadata>
