<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE guide SYSTEM "/dtd/guide.dtd">
<!-- $Header$ -->

<guide link="proj/en/desktop/kde/kde4.xml" lang="en">
<title>Gentoo KDE 4.1 Guide</title>

<author title="Author">
	<mail link="tomas.chvatal@gmail.com">Tomáš Chvátal</mail>
</author>
<author title="Author">
	<mail link="jmbsvicetto"/>
</author>
<author title="Author">
	<mail link="cryos" />
</author>

<abstract>
This guide demonstrates how to setup KDE 4.1 using the KDE team's git overlay (kde-testing). It will be updated later when the ebuilds are moved into the tree.
</abstract>

<!-- The content of this document is licensed under the CC-BY-SA license -->
<!-- See http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/2.5 -->
<license/>

<version>0.2</version>
<date>2008-09-28</date>

<chapter>
	<title>Cleaning up</title>
	<section>
		<title>Removing old KDE versions</title>
		<body>
			<p>In order to minimize issues, it is best to begin with a clean enviroment. You will need to uninstall any beta or 4.0.X release (this is needed if you are moving from any other overlay and in particular if you plan to use the -kdeprefix use flag - FHS install). Two possible ways or removing old KDE 4 installations are:</p>
			<pre caption="Unmerging commands">
# <i>emerge -C @kde-4.1 @kdebase-4.1</i> <comment>(only if you are comming from the kdesvn-portage overlay)</comment>
# <i>emerge -C $(qfile -C -q -e /usr/kde/%PREFIX%)</i> <comment>(replace %PREFIX% with your kde version, eg. 4)</comment>
			</pre>
			<pre caption="Unmerging commands (only applicable if you are moving from other overlay)">
# <i>cd /path/to/old/overlay/</i>
# <i>emerge -C $(find ./ -name \*.ebuild |sed -e "s:.ebuild::" -e "s:./::" |awk -F'/' '{print "="$1"/"$3}')</i>
			</pre>
			<p>As a final step you should remove the old overlay so that there are no conflicts with the KDE ebuilds. You should remove the old unmask and/or keyword data too.</p>
			<note>Don't forget to run depclean in order to uninstall any dependant packages.</note>
		</body>
	</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
	<title>Grabbing overlay</title>
	<section>
		<title>Using layman</title>
		<body>
			<pre caption="layman command">
# <i>layman -fS; layman -a kde-testing</i></pre>
		</body>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Using git</title>
		<body>
			<pre caption="git command">
# <i>git clone git://git.overlays.gentoo.org/proj/kde.git /PATH/WHERE/TO/PUT/OVERLAY</i></pre>
		</body>
	</section>
	<body>
		<note>The KDE 4.1 ebuilds make use of EAPI 2. Please use portage-2.2_rc11 or greater, if you run an otherwise stable profile then you must add portage to your package.keywords file.</note>
		<note>Don't forget to modify /etc/make.conf to add the overlay path to PORTDIR_OVERLAY, or to add the support for layman as required.</note>
	</body>
</chapter>

<chapter>
	<title>Unmasking/Keywording</title>
	<p>The KDE 4.1 ebuilds available from the kde-testing overlay are not masked (the masks in package.mask have been updated accordingly) and so there is no need to unmask them. If you are running the stable tree you will need to keyword the ebuilds, otherwise skip this step. For those running the stable tree in Gentoo:</p>
	<section>
		<title>Using the bundled package.keywords/kde file</title>
		<body>
			<note>This is the recomended way of keywording the KDE packages.</note>
			<p>This overlay provides an appropriate package.keywords file that can be used in your package.keywords file/directory. You can find this file in "Documentation/package.keywords" directory. Copy it to the correct location "/etc/portage/package.keywords/" (preferably make a symlink to it), or add it to your "/etc/portage/package.keywords" file.</p>
			<pre caption="Adding the file to the package.keywords directory">
# <i>cd /etc/portage/package.keywords</i>
# <i>ln -s /path/to/overlay/Documentation/package.keywords/kde .</i>
			</pre>
			<pre caption="Adding the file to the package.keywords file">
# <i>cd /etc/portage/</i>
# <i>cat /path/to/overlay/Documentation/package.keywords/kde >> package.keywords </i>
			</pre>
		</body>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Creating the file from the packages in the overlay</title>
		<body>
			<pre caption="Adding keywords to the package.keywords directory">
# <i>cd /path/to/our/overlay/</i>
# <i>find ./ -name \*.ebuild |sed -e "s:.ebuild::" -e "s:./::" |awk -F'/' '{print $1"/"$2}'  >> /etc/portage/package.keywords/kde4x</i>
# <i>cd /usr/portage/</i>
# <i>find ./x11-libs/qt-* -type d |sed -e "s:./::" |awk -F'/' '{print $1"/"$2}' | uniq >> /etc/portage/package.keywords/kde4x</i>
			</pre>
			<pre caption="Adding keywords to the package.keywords file">
# <i>cd /path/to/our/overlay/</i>
# <i>find ./ -name \*.ebuild |sed -e "s:.ebuild::" -e "s:./::" |awk -F'/' '{print $1"/"$2}' >> /etc/portage/package.keywords</i>
# <i>cd /usr/portage/</i>
# <i>find ./x11-libs/qt-* -type d |sed -e "s:./::" |awk -F'/' '{print $1"/"$2}' | uniq >> /etc/portage/package.keywords</i>
			</pre>
		</body>
	</section>
	<body>
		<note>There are some dependencies which require keywording that are not in this list. Keyword them as necessary.</note>
	</body>
</chapter>

<chapter>
	<title>Installation</title>
	<section>
		<title>The new kdeprefix use flag</title>
		<body>
			<p>The new kdeprefix use flag allows users to choose between an FHS compliant install (-kdeprefix) or a slotted install in the KDE prefix (+kdeprefix).</p>
			<p>If kdeprefix is disabled (default) KDE is installed into the FHS compliant location, i.e. /usr. That means that all of the files are put under /usr. This is the desired behavior for most users. The drawback of the FHS compliant install is that it will not be possible to have more than one minor version of KDE side by side (previous behaviour), e.g. KDE 4.1 and 4.2.</p>
			<note>This restriction does not apply to KDE 3.5 (different eclasses) or live versions (as they will continue to be installed in the /usr/kde/${live-slot}. You can have a non kdeprefix version of KDE 4.1, KDE 3.5 and a live version of KDE installed on the same system.</note>
			<p>If kdeprefix is enabled then KDE is installed into /usr/kde/${SLOT}, which allows you to install KDE 4.1, 4.2, 4.3 etc in /usr/kde/4.1, /usr/kde/4.2, /usr/kde/4.3 for example.</p>
			<warn>If you want to move between kdeprefix and -kdeprefix (or vice-versa), it is recommended that you unmerge KDE and then emerge it with the modified flag. If this is not done KDE installations can have trouble finding certain libraries/plugins.</warn>
		</body>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Using sets</title>
		<body>
			<p>One of the new features provided by portage 2.2 is sets.</p>
			<p>Sets allow the KDE team to provide a complete replacement for the monolithic packages, with the added bonus that users may choose to remove from the default sets any packages they do not want. Look in the sets directory for a list of the sets provided by the KDE team.</p>
			<p>Amongst others, there are sets for each KDE tarball - @kdeaccessibility, @kdeadmin, @kdeartwork, @kdebase, @kdeedu, @kdegames, @kdegraphics, @kdemultimedia, @kdenetwork, @kdepim, @kdesdk, @kdetoys and @kdeutils. There is also a set of sets (the equivalent to the old kde-meta package) @kde, and the same for specific versions @kde-3.5 and @kde-4x, a set for KDE deps @kdedeps, a set for optional packages @kdeoptional and a set for the split qt packages @qt-split.</p>
			<p>One can install the complete KDE by doing <i>emerge -av @kde</i>. The specific version equivalents are very useful to uninstall an old version, e.g. <i>emerge -C @kde-3.5</i>, or to reinstall all packages from a specific version, e.g. <i>emerge -av1 @kde-4x</i>. Advanced features, like removing any unwanted packages from a set, will be supported in a future release of portage - you can read more about it in <uri link="http://planet.gentoo.org/developers/genone/2008/09/25/package_set_operators">Marius Mauch (genone) blog</uri>. This code has already been commited to Portage's svn and will allow to reinstall all installed packages of a set with emerge -av @&lt;set&gt;/@installled or to have a /etc/portage/sets/kdebase-unwanted set and then run emerge -av @kdebase-@kdebase-unwanted.</p>
			<p>We strongly recommend that you install the @kdebase set in order to get a full KDE 4 session. The example below would install the kdebase set and the kdegames set.</p>
			<pre caption="emerge KDE">
# <i>emerge @kdebase @kdegames</i>
			</pre>
			<note>If you want to check the list of sets known to Portage run the following: <i>emerge --list-sets</i></note>
			<note>All KDE 4.1 ebuilds require portage-2.2_rc11 or greater, which has implemented everything in the new EAPI 2 specification used in these ebuilds.</note>
		</body>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>KDE meta packages</title>
		<body>
			<note>This method is provided to ease the transition to the new sets. There will no meta ebuilds for KDE 4.2.</note>
			<pre caption="emerge meta packages">
# <i>emerge kde-meta:4.1</i></pre>
		</body>
	</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
	<title>Configuration</title>
	<body>
		<p>KDE stores its configuration files in the <i>~/.kde</i> directory by default. In the Gentoo ebuilds this has been changed in KDE 4.1 to allow for better integration of KDE 3.5 and 4.1 when using the same user account. If you export KDEHOME this behaviour will be overridden. It is strongly recommended that you do not do this. KDEHOME will make KDE 3.5 and 4.1 use the same configuration directory which is not usually desired.</p>
		<p>KDE 3.5 uses <i>~/.kde</i> and the default FHS (-kdeprefix) KDE 4.1 uses <i>~/.kde4</i>. If you install KDE 4.1 using the kdeprefix use flag then the configuration directory will default to <i>~/.kde4.1</i>, <i>~/.kde4.2</i> etc. The advantage of this is that KDE 3.5 and 4.1 can be run from the same user account without clobbering settings. Moving backwards in version, i.e. 4.1 to 3.5, is not supported.</p>
		<p>Settings are not migrated by default. If you want to attempt to migrate your settings you should copy your old configuration directory to the new location before logging in. For example,</p>
		<pre caption="copy configuration directory">
$ <i>cp -r ~/.kde ~/.kde4</i></pre>
		<p>If this is successful then your settings should all be migrated. If not it is possible to log out and remove the new configuration directory to start with a clean configuration directory.</p>
	</body>
</chapter>
<chapter>
	<title>Migration from KDE 3.X</title>
	<section>
		<title>Configuration transition</title>
		<body>
			<p>TODO</p>
		</body>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Removing kde-3.5</title>
		<body>
			<pre caption="Unmerging kde-3.5">
# <i>emerge -C @kde-3.5</i>
			</pre>
			<note>Run depclean in order to remove all dependent packages.</note>
		</body>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>No Desktop icon</title>
		<body>
			<p>KDE 4, as it moves towards a semantic desktop, did not bundle an icon for the desktop.</p>
			<p>The desktop icon can be replaced with the standard folder icon using the following command.</p>
			<pre caption="sed command">
$ <i>sed -i -e "s:Icon=desktop:Icon=folder:g" ~/Desktop/.directory</i></pre>
		</body>
	</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
	<title>Hints</title>
	<section>
		<title>kde-misc/plasmoids</title>
		<body>
			<p>This ebuild contains various plasmoids that were requested by users (if you find others that would be useful to our user community please contact us, svn version will not be added and it must work with KDE 4.1).</p>
		</body>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>x11-themes/plasma-themes</title>
		<body>
			<p>This ebuild contains various plasma themes. The procedure for requesting additional themes is the same as that for plasmoids.</p>
		</body>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>x11-themes/gtk-engines-qt</title>
		<body>
			<p>This ebuild should be used if you want your gtk applications to use a similar them to the Qt/KDE applications. Configuration can be found in systemsetings->Apperance->GTK Styles and Fonts.</p>
		</body>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>x11-themes/gtk-engines-qtcurve</title>
		<body>
			<p>Another approach to making gtk/qt3/qt4 applications looks the same. You must also install x11-themes/qtcurve-qt4 for this to work with Qt 4/KDE 4 applications.</p>
		</body>
	</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
	<title>Uninstalling KDE-4x</title>
	<section>
		<title>Removing all KDE packages</title>
		<body>
			<p>In order to remove all KDE 4 packages and dependant packages:</p>
			<pre caption="Unmerging commands">
# <i>emerge -C @kde-4x</i>
# <i>cd /path/to/our/overlay/</i>
# <i>emerge -C $(find ./ -name \*.ebuild |sed -e "s:.ebuild::" -e "s:./::" |awk -F'/' '{print "="$1"/"$3}')</i></pre>
		</body>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Rebuilding the application database</title>
		<body>
			<p>To rebuild the KDE 3 application database run:</p>
			<pre caption="kbuildsycoca command">
# kbuildsycoca --noincremental</pre>
		</body>
	</section>
</chapter>
</guide>
